Uzmar de Jesús Gómez Yáñez

CURRICULUM VITAE



MSc Scientific Computing and Data Analysis

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Learned to program throughout the Physics career, mainly in scientific computing topics. Hands-on experience applying Machine Learning algorithms to real business problems. Excellent usage of GNU / Linux systems and knowledge of object-oriented programming languages such as Python and C++. I have also worked in the academic field as a teacher assistant, teaching mathematics, computer science, physics and other topics at a university level. Good understanding of algorithms, data structures, bayesian statistics, etc.

PERSONAL DATA

ADDRESS: Durham, England PHONE: +44 7704 613361

EMAIL: uzmar.gomez@ciencias.unam.mx
LINKEDIN: www.linkedin.com/in/uzmargomez
GITHUB: https://github.com/uzmargomez

EDUCATION

PRESENT | MSc in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis, Department of Computer Science, Durham University,

Durham, United Kingdom.

2021 Specialization: Earth and Environmental Sciences

OVERALL SCORE: - Detailed List of Grades

Dissertation: "GPU Programming with Standard C++"

Description:

2018 BSc in Physics, Faculty of Science, National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), Mexico City,

1exico.

2011 Dissertation: "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric"

Description: Creation of a finite differences scheme that evolves the relativistic Vlasov equation on a

black hole metric background, assuming this is an advective equation, with velocities

dependent both on time and position.

Advisor: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

OVERALL SCORE: 9.37/10 Detailed List of Grades

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming Languages | Python, C++, Fortran, Julia

Machine/Deep Learning | TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, Facebook Prophet, ARIMA, SARIMA, LDA, PCA,

Kmeans, KNN, Neural Networks, Recommendation systems, Classification

and Regression problems

Serving Seldon Core, TFServing Databases SQL, MongoDB

Containers Docker, Kubernetes
Operating Systems GNU/Linux, Windows

Web Backend | Flask

Web Frontend | HTML (Plotly Dash), Bootstrap

Version Control | Gi

Parallel Computing | C++ Standard Algorithms, CUDA Python

Data Visualization | Plotly Dash, Qlik, Tableau

GCP Tools (Console and CLI) | BigQuery, BQ ML, Compute Engine, Composer, Artifact Registry, Kubernetes

Engine, Storage, Data Studio, Kubeflow, Data Fusion, Cloud Build, VertexAI

LANGUAGES

ENGLISH: C1 Level - IELTS (2021)
SPANISH: Mothertongue

FRENCH: Basic

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

Academic

Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Numerical Analysis, General Relativity, Numerical Relativity, Black Holes

Non academic

Science Fiction and Fantasy Reading, Videogames, Running, Swimming, Playing Guitar, Traveling.

EXPERIENCE

Short Description

Jul 2020 - Jan 2022. Data Scientist at Rackspace Technology. I helped on the migration of data from on-premises servers to the GCP cloud. I worked on churn prediction models that used features related to the COVID19 spreading aside from other business-related features to predict customer attrition, this work includes the development of the model using XGBoost, as well as the deployment of it using Kubeflow and the serving via Seldon Core. I was also involved in constructing an SSAS OLAP Cube to be used by the company for inventory-related queries. I worked on NLP tasks, such as the extraction of themes out of tickets using semantic similarity, by getting embeddings vectors out of sentences with a transformer architecture named Universal Sentence Encoder. Worked on how to translate voice to text. I built two production-level applications using Plotly Dash.

Dec 2019 - Jun 2020. Data Scientist at Softtek. I worked on a face recognition system using a method called Sparse Representation and another one using Neural Networks. I acquired a deep understanding of Neural Networks for Face Detection and Recognition, Image Classification, Language Processing, among others, as well as some experience in Data Visualization tools such as Tableau.

Sep 2019 - Dec 2019. Data Scientist Trainee at Softtek. I learned about different statistical and machine learning techniques, as well as algorithms, to study a wide variety of problems.

2016 - 2019. As mentioned below, I have taught Computer Science classes, in which the Python programming language was introduced to Physics students.

Sep 2018 - Dec 2019. I have research experience using the Einstein Toolkit, a software platform created for supporting research in relativistic astrophysics and gravitational physics.

Subjects I have taught:

- Computer Science.
 - https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/102.pdf
- Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation 1. https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/docencia/horarios/presentacion/295997
- Relativity

https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/718.pdf

- Mathematics I for Applied Sciences.
 http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1118.pdf
- Mathematics II for Applied Sciences. http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1216.pdf

EXTRA CURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

PRESENT OCT 2021 Student Representative MiSCaDA Programme

Durham University

Provide a link between students and the University Staff. Sit on the Student/Staff Comittee to discuss issues within the department raised by the students

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

| MAY 2022 JAN 2022 | Volunteer Durham Foodbank Assisted with the distribution of food to people in need. |
|----------------------|---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------|
| DEC 2021 Jun 2021 | Teacher Casa de la Sal Support children with HIV on various Mathematics and English Language assignments. |
| SEP 2019 MAR 2019 | Teacher University Student Council (CEU México) Provide tools to university students to help develop their academic, professional and personal skills, to facilitate their employment and the definition of their life project. |

MAR 2019 | Volunteer

SEP 2018 | Adopt a Talent Program (PAUTA)

Encourage scientific vocation so that those children and adolescents who like science and have outstanding skills, find a space where they can share their interest and learn from each other.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

| SEP 2019 JAN 2017 | Fellow Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves (Red ANyOG, CONACYT). |
|----------------------|--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------|
| _ | Student Associate Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM. |
| 3 | Student Associate Institute of Physics, UNAM. |

PRESENTATIONS AND POSTER SESSIONS

| OCT 11, 2017 | Poster Presentation at LX NATIONAL CONGRESS OF PHYSICS. |
|--------------|-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------|
| | Monterrey, Mexico |
| | Presentation of a poster about my undergraduate thesis "Numerical Study of Vlasov |
| | Faustion in the Schwarzschild Metric" |

SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONORS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

| 2017 | Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Proyect |
|------|------------------------------------------------------------------------------|
| 2016 | Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT). |
| 1 | , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , , |
| 2016 | Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Undergraduate School |
| 2015 | Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT). |

REFERENCES

NAME: Dr. Tobias Weinzierl

OCCUPATION: Professor in the Department of Computer Science at Durham University

LINKEDIN: tobias.weinzierl@durham.ac.uk

NAME: Dr. Charles Mueller OCCUPATION: Senior Engineer at Amazon

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/charles-n-mueller/

NAME: Dr. Fernando Herrera
OCCUPATION: Senior Data Engineer at Revolut

LINKEDIN: https://www.linkedin.com/in/fernando-jose-herrera-elizalde-76a32790/

NAME: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

INSTITUTION NAME: Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

OCCUPATION: Director, Researcher, Teacher EMAIL: malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx

UPDATED ON AUGUST 8, 2022

Master of Science in Scientific Computing and Data Analysis

Durham University Grades

| Course | GRADE | CREDITS |
|---------------------------------------------------------------------------------|-----------------------------|-----------|
| Project | | 60 |
| Professional Skills | 7.92 | 15 |
| Core la: Introduction to Machine Learning and Statistics | 9.15 | 15 |
| Core Ib: Introduction to Scientific and High-Performance Computing | 7.95 | 15 |
| Performance Engineering and Advanced Algorithms | 7.5 | 15 |
| Advanced Statistics and Machine Learning: Foundations and Unsupervised Learning | 9.0 | 15 |
| Advanced Statistics and Machine Learning: Regression and Classification | 9.15 | 15 |
| Earth and Environmental Sciences | Sciences 6.76 Total Credits | 30 180 |
| | OVERALL SCORE | |

OVERALL SCORE

Bachelor of Science in Physics

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) Grades

| Course | Grade | CREDITS |
|------------------------------------------------------------|---------------|---------|
| Differential and Integral Calculus I | 07 | 18 |
| Algebra | 10 | 10 |
| Computer Science | 10 | 6 |
| Analytic Geometry I | 08 | 10 |
| Differential and Integral Calculus II | 10 | 18 |
| Contemporary Physics | 09 | 6 |
| Vector Mechanics | 9 | 12 |
| Analytic Geometry II | 09 | 10 |
| Mechanics Laboratory | 10 | 6 |
| Collective Phenomena | 10 | 12 |
| Collective Phenomena Laboratory | 09 | 6 |
| Linear Algebra I | 10 | 10 |
| Differential Equations I | 08 | 10 |
| Optics | 09 | 12 |
| Linear Algebra II | 10 | 10 |
| Differential and Integral Calculus III | 07 | 18 |
| Electromagnetism I | 9 | 12 |
| Electromagnetism Laboratory | 10 | 6 |
| Tensor Calculus | 9 | 10 |
| Differential and Integral Calculus IV | 07 | 18 |
| Introduction to Quantum Physics | 10 | 12 |
| Optics Laboratory | 10 | 6 |
| Thermodynamics | 09 | 12 |
| Advanced Mathematics of Physics | 10 | 10 |
| Computational Physics | 10 | 12 |
| Quantum Mechanics | 09 | 12 |
| Complex Variable I | 10 | 10 |
| Selected Topics of Mathematics and Theoretical Physics | 10 | 6 |
| Electromagnetism II | 08 | 12 |
| Electronics Laboratory | 10 | 6 |
| Statistical Physics | 10 | 12 |
| Contemporary Physics Laboratory I | 10 | 6 |
| Complex Variable II | 10 | 10 |
| Analytical Mechanics | 10 | 12 |
| Relativity | 09 | 06 |
| Introduction to Elementary Particle Physics I | 10 | 06 |
| Dynamics of Deformable Bodies | 10 | 12 |
| Atomic Physics and Condensed Matter | 09 | 06 |
| Nuclear and Subnuclear Physics | 09 | 06 |
| Contemporary Physics Laboratory II | 10 | 06 |
| Topology and Differential Geometry for Physics | 10 | 06 |
| Selected Topics of Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation I | 10 | 06 |
| Selected Topics of Computational Physics I | 10 | 06 |
| English Language | AC | 00 |
| | Total Credits | 418 |
| | OVERALL SCORE | 9.37 |